<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>PILOSA.EU</title><link>http://pilosa.eu/</link><description></description><atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><item><title>EPA SWMM / Giswater Tutorial 2: Project Setup</title><link>http://pilosa.eu/blog/2014/09/20/swmm-giswater-tutorial-2-project-setup/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This is the 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt;  episode in my tutorial on the using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; Storm Water Management Model (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWMM&lt;/span&gt;) and Giswater for rainfall-runoff modeling for an urban drainage network system. This episodes describes how to create new project in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWMM&lt;/span&gt;, how to create a project using Giswater and the initial options that need to be set before we can start creating our&amp;nbsp;network. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="epa-swwm"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWWM&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting a new project in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWMM&lt;/span&gt; is a simple as starting up the program. A new project is opened and you can directly start drawing a sewer network. A project can be saved as a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWMM&lt;/span&gt;-input file (&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;INP&lt;/span&gt;-file&lt;/strong&gt;). Such an input-file contains both all objects in a project&amp;#8217;s network and all options set by the user. Since a standard set of default values is provided, we could start drawing the network without further preparation. Most options deal with the look-and-feel of the program and the simulation parameters. For these options, we will keep the default values for now. Some options however do affect the drawing of the network and will need to be set&amp;nbsp;beforehand:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="SWMM_Defaults" src="/images/SWMM_defaults.png" title="Default prefixes for EPA SWMM objects." /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specify whether the automatic computation of conduit lengths and subcatchment areas is turned on or&amp;nbsp;off.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose whether the positions of links above the invert of their connecting nodes are expressed as a Depth above the node invert or as the Elevation of the&amp;nbsp;offset.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select flow units that makes sense (i.e. change the default Cubic Feet per Second to Cubic Metres per Second).
&lt;li&gt;Change the map dimensions and extent to appropriate values (available from the menu: &lt;strong&gt;View &lt;i class="fa fa-long-arrow-right"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Dimensions&lt;/strong&gt;).
&lt;li&gt;On the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ID&lt;/span&gt; Labels page of the defaults menu (&lt;strong&gt;Project &lt;i class="fa fa-long-arrow-right"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Defaults&lt;/strong&gt;), set the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ID&lt;/span&gt; Prefixes as follows (leave the others blank):
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rain Gages: &lt;strong&gt;Gage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subcatchments: &lt;strong&gt;S&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Junctions: &lt;strong&gt;J&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Outfalls:  &lt;strong&gt;Out&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conduits: &lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ID&lt;/span&gt; Increment: &lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will make &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWMM&lt;/span&gt; automatically label new objects with consecutive numbers following the  designated&amp;nbsp;prefix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="giswater"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GISWATER&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id="software-configuration"&gt;Software&amp;nbsp;configuration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The software configuration window can be opened from the menu (&lt;strong&gt;Configuration&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;i class="fa fa-long-arrow-right"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Software configuration&lt;/strong&gt;). The options that can be set here determine how Giswater deals with inputfiles, outputfiles and the database. For these options, we keep the default values. If you would use your own database, this is the place where you can set up the location of the database administration program (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PGADMIN3&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="database-connection"&gt;Database&amp;nbsp;connection&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The software configuration window can be opened from the menu (&lt;strong&gt;Configuration&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;i class="fa fa-long-arrow-right"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Database configuration&lt;/strong&gt;). If I remember correctly, this was all working correctly without alterations for the included portable postgis database. If you would use your own database, this is the place where you can set up the&amp;nbsp;connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="creating-a-epa-swmm-project"&gt;Creating a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWMM&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;project&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to start a project in Giswater is to load the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWMM&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DB&lt;/span&gt; Sample project.
The corresponding option in the project menu loads a sample project into the db using the sql files in the installation directory. You can do this an play around for a while. The goal for this episode in my tutorial is to create an empty project, so we&amp;#8217;ll take a different&amp;nbsp;track:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWMM&lt;/span&gt; window (&lt;strong&gt;Software&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;i class="fa fa-long-arrow-right"&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWMM&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;):&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Giswater_EPA_SWMM" src="/images/Giswater_EPA_SWMM.png" title="Giswater EPA SWMM window." /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a project and supply the following characteristics:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Name of the&amp;nbsp;project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Title of the&amp;nbsp;project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Author of the&amp;nbsp;project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Date&amp;nbsp;create&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SRID&lt;/span&gt; of the coordinate system to be&amp;nbsp;used&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Giswater_create_project" src="/images/Giswater_create_project.png" title="Giswater create project window." /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pressing the options button would open en windows in which we can set a broad array of options. A few of the affect  our system have sensible defaults Options: sensible defaults, so we keep them as&amp;nbsp;is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="creating-a-gis-project"&gt;Creating a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GIS&lt;/span&gt;-project&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After we created the project, all necessary tables are present so theoretically we could start filling these tables with information about our system. However, these tables are not yet easy accessible for the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GIS&lt;/span&gt; superpowers yet. In order to facilitate this, Giswater contains a function to create a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GIS&lt;/span&gt;-project that can be opened and modified using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QGIS&lt;/span&gt;. During this process, a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QGIS&lt;/span&gt;-project is created with the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWMM&lt;/span&gt; data (i.e. the objects in the system and input tables) and simulation analysis in its table of&amp;nbsp;contents. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Giswater_create_gisproject" src="/images/Giswater_create_gisproject.png" title="Giswater create GIS-project window." /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I could should you our tutorial project in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QGIS&lt;/span&gt;, yet that would look somewhat empty in it&amp;#8217;s current state. Therefore I&amp;#8217;ll provide a screenshot of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GIS&lt;/span&gt;-project created based on the sample&amp;nbsp;project:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="QGIS_sample_epaswmm" src="/images/QGIS_sample_epaswmm.png" title="Sample EPA SWMM project in QGIS." /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="conclusions"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CONCLUSIONS&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting a new project in Giswater is a little more work than in vanilla &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWMM&lt;/span&gt;. This amount of work however is still very small. Creating a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GIS&lt;/span&gt;-project is trivial and gives us the opportunity to visualize and edit our system in a proper &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GIS&lt;/span&gt;-environment with the possibility to add our own data. background maps, web services etc.&amp;nbsp;etc.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Erwin Sterrenburg</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:pilosa.eu,2014-09-20:blog/2014/09/20/swmm-giswater-tutorial-2-project-setup/</guid><category>SWMM</category><category>Giswater</category><category>Water</category></item><item><title>EPA SWMM / Giswater Tutorial 1: Installation</title><link>http://pilosa.eu/blog/2014/09/10/swmm-giswater-tutorial-1-installation/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This is the 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; episode in my tutorial on the using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; Storm Water Management Model (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWMM&lt;/span&gt;) and Giswater for rainfall-runoff modeling for an urban drainage network system. This episodes describes the installation&amp;nbsp;process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The instructions in the &lt;a href="http://www.giswater.org/print/book/export/html/17"&gt;Giswater documentation&lt;/a&gt; provided sufficient information for installing this software. To install you must download the installer package and execute it. Remember you can choose the &lt;a href="http://download.giswater.org/giswater_stand-alone.exe"&gt;Giswater stand-alone install package&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href="http://download.giswater.org/giswater_all-in-one.exe"&gt;all-in-one install package&lt;/a&gt;. The all-in-one installer package is designed with a portable version of PostgreSQL+PostGIS 2.1. Remember you need to have installed an updated Java Runtime Environment (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;JRE&lt;/span&gt;) on your&amp;nbsp;computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took the easy road and used the all-in-one installer. Installation using the installation wizard proved to be straight-forward. When the dust had settled, the following had taken&amp;nbsp;place:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Giswater had been placed in it&amp;#8217;s standard installation path (&lt;strong&gt;C:\Program Files\Giswater\&lt;/strong&gt;, so apparently it&amp;#8217;s a 64-bit application) with the following sub-folders:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;epa&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPANET&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWMM&lt;/span&gt; command line&amp;nbsp;executables;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;gis&lt;/strong&gt; - templates for gisproject&amp;nbsp;export(?);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;images&lt;/strong&gt; - images used in the Giswater graphical user&amp;nbsp;interface;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;inp&lt;/strong&gt; - sqlite-databases used in the information exchange between the database and the input / output files of the simulation tools &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; templates for these&amp;nbsp;files;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;legal&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPL&lt;/span&gt; v3&amp;nbsp;license;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;lib&lt;/strong&gt; - java libraries used by the Giswater&amp;nbsp;application;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;samples&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt;-scripts containing data for sample&amp;nbsp;projects;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sql&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SQL&lt;/span&gt;-scripts containing database&amp;nbsp;logic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some additional folders had been placed in &lt;strong&gt;C:\Users\&amp;lt;username&amp;gt;\Giswater\&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;config&lt;/strong&gt; - some general configuration&amp;nbsp;files;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;log&lt;/strong&gt; - logging directory for giswater&amp;nbsp;application;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;portable&lt;/strong&gt; - portable installation of postgresql + postgis +&amp;nbsp;pgadmin3.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="epa-swwm"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWWM&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since one of my objectives is to make a comparison between using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWMM&lt;/span&gt; toghether with Giswater and a vanilla &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWMM&lt;/span&gt; setup, I also need to have &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWMM&lt;/span&gt; 5.0.022 installed (the only version supported by Giswater). However, this version is not available anymore from the &lt;a href="http://www2.epa.gov/water-research/storm-water-management-model-swmm"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; website&lt;/a&gt;. After about 3 years of sleep, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWMM&lt;/span&gt; model is actively developed again. Usually this is good news, but when other products depend on older versions that have been taken offline, it is bad news as&amp;nbsp;well&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this tutorial, it won&amp;#8217;t be a problem, since I already had version 5.0.022 installed on my computer. Yet, there is a bigger issue here: a lot of functionality with regard to the visualization of the simulation results (charts, profiles, animations, etc.) is not possible without the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWMM&lt;/span&gt; graphical user interface. Following could be done to make this functionality also available to Giswater users (in order of personal&amp;nbsp;preference):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Giswater developers keep their software compatible with the most recent version of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWMM&lt;/span&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; also makes version 5.0.022 available for download, since this has been the stable version for almost 3&amp;nbsp;years;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Giswater developers also supply a download for the full version of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EPA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SWMM&lt;/span&gt; 5.0.022, not just the command line&amp;nbsp;version.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s hope one of the parties involved reads this and takes action to solve this issue &lt;i class="fa fa-smile-o"&gt;&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Erwin Sterrenburg</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:pilosa.eu,2014-09-10:blog/2014/09/10/swmm-giswater-tutorial-1-installation/</guid><category>SWMM</category><category>Giswater</category><category>Water</category></item><item><title>Why Pilosa?</title><link>http://pilosa.eu/blog/2014/09/02/why-pilosa/</link><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I reject holism. I challenge you to tell me, for instance, how a holistic
description of an ant colony sheds any more light on it than is shed by a
description of the ants inside it, and their roles, and their interrelationships.
Any holistic explanation of an ant colony will inevitably fall far short of
explaining where the consciousness experienced by an ant colony arises from.
&lt;cite&gt;Dr. Anteater in &amp;#8220;Ant Fugue&amp;#8221;, part of  &amp;#8220;Gödel, Escher, Bach: An Eternal Golden Braid&amp;#8221; by Douglas R. Hofstadter&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s humans that are the most curious animal on the&amp;nbsp;planet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;img src="/images/tamandua.png" alt="Tamandua" title="Wise and curious anteater" /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;T&lt;/b&gt;ool for&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;A&lt;/b&gt;llocation&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;M&lt;/b&gt;anagement&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;u&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;N&lt;/b&gt;der &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;D&lt;/b&gt;ecentralization&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;U&lt;/b&gt;sing&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;b&gt;A&lt;/b&gt;gents&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This thesis addresses the interdependencies between water use and water
 availability and describes a model that has been developed to increase
 insight in the potential effects of different decentralization regimes
 in water allocation management with regard to the spatial and temporal
 distribution of water availability and agricultural water use in a
 semi-arid river&amp;nbsp;basin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relevant processes include physical processes such as hydrological processes,
 water user responses to variations and changes in water availability and social processes
 between water users and water&amp;nbsp;managers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results are relevant for research on relevant initial condition,
 context factors and design principles for participative river basin management.
 Water demand, water allocation management and water availability are strongly
 related in semi-arid environments, where the irrigation sector is responsible
 for a large part of consumptive water use. Variations in water abstractions
 for irrigation depend on irrigated area and irrigation requirements per&amp;nbsp;hectare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All Tamanduas share a fascination for ants: the usual Tamandua (meaning
&amp;#8220;anteater&amp;#8221; in both Tupi and Portuguese) tends to see them as a tasty
snack. This Tamandua however, uses ants - a common metaphor for
agents - to analyze a complex system. When observing natural ant
colonies it can easily be seen that the complexity of each single ant is
rather low. Nonetheless ant colonies exhibit complex behavior and have
even been able to demonstrate the ability to solve geometric problems.
Water allocation management in a river catchment is another example
of such a complex system: relatively simple actions and decisions of
autonomous stakeholders can lead to complex water scarcity patterns.
Tamandua aims to increase insight in what is going on in the &amp;#8220;ant colony
of water&amp;nbsp;allocation&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-this-name"&gt;Why this&amp;nbsp;name?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plan was to use tamandua:
a name I came up with for .. model developed during my graduation &amp;#8230; fond of ever&amp;nbsp;since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr&amp;nbsp;anteater&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tamandua + meanying +&amp;nbsp;image&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However: domains already taken
One step up: pilosa = &amp;#8230;&amp;nbsp;Sloths&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Xenartha
Doodles  .. armadillo-like creature + image&amp;nbsp;Many&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Erwin Sterrenburg</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:pilosa.eu,2014-09-02:blog/2014/09/02/why-pilosa/</guid><category>PYTHON</category><category>BLOG</category></item><item><title>Why Pelican?</title><link>http://pilosa.eu/blog/2014/09/01/why-pelican/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The idea of a personal website and blog had been floating around in my 
head for a long long time. Most of this time, I expected the result
to be powered by &lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com/" title="Django"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt; /
&lt;a href="http://mezzanine.jupo.org/" title="Mezzanine"&gt;Mezzanine&lt;/a&gt;.
Some weeks ago, I finally got to work and set things into motion. The result 
however was not really satisfying. All functionality was there and 
the looks kept making me happy, yet the approach felt like overkill
for my simple&amp;nbsp;needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some internet research for alternatives opened up
a whole world of static site generators that seemed much 
more appropriate for a site like this. Among these, I&amp;#8217;ve chosen
&lt;a href="http://blog.getpelican.com/" title="Pelican"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; for the following&amp;nbsp;reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it is written in familiar language (python) and uses a familiar template system&amp;nbsp;(jinja2);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it&amp;#8217;s extensive collection of themes and&amp;nbsp;plugins;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the documentation is elaborate and many fellow bloggers have written helpful posts
 on how to use and customize&amp;nbsp;Pelican;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pelicans are awesome!&lt;sup id="fnref:staticgenerators"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:staticgenerators" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="awesome pelican" src="/images/pelican.jpg" title="Awesome pelican" /&gt; 
&lt;cite&gt;By &lt;a href="http://carolinabirds.org/" title="DickDaniels"&gt;DickDaniels&lt;/a&gt; (Own work), &lt;a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0" title="CC-BY-SA-3.0"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CC&lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BY&lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SA&lt;/span&gt;-3.0&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html" title="GFDL"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GFDL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, via Wikimedia Commons&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The only big con of this approach is the need to use a 3rd party service for comments.&lt;sup id="fnref:staticcomments"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:staticcomments" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
The most widely used comment hosting service is Disqus, which I implemented here as well since it&amp;#8217;s
omnipresence suggest they must do something right. After&amp;nbsp;all:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fifty million Frenchmen can&amp;#8217;t be&amp;nbsp;wrong&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None-the-less using a service that I have blocked by Ghostery during most of my
browsing time feels somewhat wrong, so this might change in the&amp;nbsp;future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-this-theme"&gt;Why this&amp;nbsp;theme?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theme I created for Mezzanine consisted of a dark color scheme
with a dynamically generated fractal background.
After moving to Pelican, I looked at the available themes to see which 
of these would form the best starting point to re-create this look.
However, when I encountered the pure theme, this theme seemed to be 
almost good enough without further modification. 
The only drawback was a severe shortage of bananas, but that was easy
enough to solve. Bananas improve&amp;nbsp;everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:staticgenerators"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well-chosen names seem to be common among static site generators: 
&lt;a href="http://getnikola.com/"&gt;Nikola Tesla&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://octopress.org/"&gt;Octopuses&lt;/a&gt;
 are awesome as well!&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:staticgenerators" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:staticcomments"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatives do exist like using the
 &lt;a href="https://github.com/getpelican/pelican-plugins/tree/master/pelican_comment_system"&gt;Pelican comment system&lt;/a&gt;
 plugin or hosting your own comment service using
 &lt;a href="http://posativ.org/isso/"&gt;Isso&lt;/a&gt;, yet would take some of the simplicity of a static site generator approach away.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:staticcomments" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Erwin Sterrenburg</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:pilosa.eu,2014-09-01:blog/2014/09/01/why-pelican/</guid><category>PYTHON</category><category>BLOG</category></item><item><title>Hello World</title><link>http://pilosa.eu/blog/2014/08/28/hello-world/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who am&amp;nbsp;I?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why a&amp;nbsp;blog?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What to expect&amp;nbsp;here?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;practical excercise
naslagwerk, zowel voor mijzelf als voor&amp;nbsp;anderen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both professional  and .. projects, valuable addition to&amp;nbsp;documentation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the posts and leave a comment if you feel like&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Erwin Sterrenburg</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:pilosa.eu,2014-08-28:blog/2014/08/28/hello-world/</guid><category>BLOG</category></item></channel></rss>